I. 人员变动
In 1996 after Id Software dropped Quake and John Romero,
1996年，在id放弃了《雷神之锤》，开除了John Romero之后
they were looking to go in another direction with their next project,
他们正在为下一个游戏寻找创意上的方向
Which wasn't always gonna be called Quake II
这个游戏不是一开始就叫做《雷神之锤II》的
There were other ideas for the title like "WOR" with an "O",
当时还有其他的想法，诸如WOR等
but everybody just decided to call it Quake II,
不过他们还是起名为《雷神之锤II》了
Despite the fact that it has nothing to do with the first game.
虽然和首作没啥关系就对了
As explained by Tim Willits, Id co-owner and designer for, uh... 25 years now.
根据id的股东，以及在其中担任设计工作25年的Tim Willits
The first Quake game was kind of a mess to develop
《雷神之锤》首作开发的过程可谓一团糟
and so everyone decided to have a clearer vision of what the game should be.
所以，大家决定要对游戏的开发有一个清晰的路线
Sc-fi! Space marines!
那就是科幻风和宇宙飞船！
Remember, this was 1997 and the
先说一下，当时是1997年
"big, tough space marine" trope hadn't been worn quite as thin:
“魁梧难缠的太空战士”的说法还没过时
one man fighting against an army of horrible villains.
比如一个人为了爱兔而干翻地狱啥的
An inspiration cited by the devs was The Guns of Navarone,
开发者曾经借鉴了这部电影的想法
注：The Guns of Navarone(纳瓦隆大炮)是1961年于美国上映的二战片
a movie about a unit of commandos in WWII
电影是关于二战时期一个突击队
sent to destroy artillery so that the British Navy
被派遣毁坏敌方大炮，进而大英帝国海军
could rescue trapped soldiers from the Germans
可以从纳粹那里救出被困士兵
I haven't seen it; the movie is older than my parents.
我反正是没看过，这电影比我父母还老
He says, after referencing The Cabinet of Dr. Caligari
他们在那期讲DOS啥的视频里，引述完某个更老的电影之后说的
in a video about DOS trash.
So the story of Quake II,
那么，《雷神之锤II》的剧情嘛......
don't get too excited, there's still barely story in this game
好吧，别太激动，这个游戏还是老样子，没多少剧情
takes its cues from WWII and not HP Lovecraft
大多数是借鉴那个二战相关电影，而不是克苏鲁啥的
注：Howard Phillips Lovecraft，美国恐怖、科幻与奇幻小说作家。
他最著名的作品是后来被称为“克苏鲁神话”（Cthulhu Mythos）的一系列小说。
大家也可以去听Metallica的The Call of Ktulu
and from the beginning it was gonna be a more
并且从游戏开始，你会感受到较上一个作品
focused, polished, impressive game than its predecessor,
这个游戏的目标更加明显，制作更精良，让人印象深刻
which is funny because Quake II is probably remembered less fondly.
而这就有点搞笑了，它或许是整个系列作里最少被人所提及的了
Quake 1 had a certain spirit; an atmosphere,
《雷神之锤》一代有那种特殊的灵魂，那种气氛
certainly helped by Trent Reznor's soundtrack
很明显都是Trent Reznor制作的原声带所烘托的
注：你们把Trent Reznor当作Nine Inch Nail就好了
Trent Reznor was asked to come back and refused after seeing the game itself,
Trent Reznor被请回来，他看了游戏之后拒绝制作原声带
saying something i've seen reported as the charitable
记得新闻报过，说他虽然想义务制作，但是
“这个游戏没有那味了。”
Quake 2 was a turning point for Id Software, I think,
我觉得对于id来说，《雷神之锤II》算是一个转折点
where the scrappy little company that made deeply influential games
他从一个制作了很多有重大影响游戏的，又破又小的公司
became a real company,
变成了一个真正的公司
With like, responsible employees.
有很多有责任心的员工
Nice, dedicated people who lacked the cult of personality that would surround others.
这些人很好，很敬业，然而不像之前那样个性鲜明了
Not to mention Tom Hall and John Romero were off at Ion Storm,
更不必说Tom Hall和John Romero被开除后创建了Ion Storm
注：John Romero 的 Daikatana 可谓让其身败名裂
Sandy Peterson moved on to Ensemble Studios
Sandy Peterson去Ensemble Studios开发帝国时代去了
Perfected human analogue and Jace Hall asphyxiator, John Carmack
而Civvie心中的完美大神以及能让Jace Hall窒息的辣个男人嘛
注：Jace Hall是一位制作人，参与了F.E.A.R的开发与发行，就是那个黑人
"I would be going to strangle from the rear."
“我要从后面向你发起进♂攻”
"That was the weirdest sensation I've ever had in my whole life, did you get that on camera?"
“刚那感觉我这辈子头一回体验，你从摄像机回放看到了吧”
"That was awesome dude"
“刚那下挺好的”
"It's a good thing you didn't wet your pants"
“幸亏你的裤子还没湿掉”
Carmack did the thing where he made a new engine,
这家伙开发了一个新引擎
or, more of an avancement of the previous one that made it a bit more colourful.
或者说，是把上一个Quake引擎改进了一下，变得更加彩色
But he didn't do skeletal animations,
但是他没有实现骨骼动画
what the fuck was he thinking there?
他为啥不再多写点功能呢？
Anyway, Adrian Carmack and American McGee were still around
无论如何，这俩人都还在
美工兼创始人Adrian Carmack
设计师American MaGee
But this was a different Id Software.
但对于id来说，却有点不同了
Maybe there time had come and gone when it came to truly revolutionising things
也许对于真正具有革命性的东西来说，真就是后浪拍前浪呗
A year later would bring Half-Life, and also Unreal,
一年后《半条命》和《虚幻》就上市了
which was built as a "Quake killer" when it started,
当年可是按照“雷神之锤的终结者”的标准来开发的
and I think it succeeded. I find it's a better Quake II than Quake II is.
我觉得也是做到了，我觉得《虚幻》比《雷神之锤II》好玩多了
I'm not as familiar with Quake 2; I haven't played it as much as Quake, or Doom, or Doom 3,
我对《雷神之锤II》不是那么熟悉，不像一代《雷神之锤》
或是《毁灭战士》，《毁灭战士III》，乃至《德军总部3D》
or probably even Wolfenstein 3D.
But I was genuinely curious what playing on the hardest skill would be like.
但我还是对最高难度会是啥样很感兴趣
Vanilla Quake 2 doesn't let you select the hardest skill,
原版《雷神之锤II》没法让你选择最高难度
skill 3, also known as hard+.
也就是第三难度，通称“困难+”
Thankfully Yamagi Quake II, the port I'm using, calls it nightmare and lets you select it.
万幸的是，我用的改进引擎将其命名为“噩梦难度”，并可以选择
注：《雷神之锤II》引擎于2001年11月开源
This, I feel, helps the game significantly
我觉得，对于带动我的精力来说，还挺管用的
Because I would often get bored around Ammo Depot and drop the game entirely.
因为我经常在Ammo Depot这关厌倦了，然后弃游了
I've beaten it before, hell, Quake 2 was the first game I ever deathmatched online in.
我当然通关了，而且这游戏还是我第一个在网上死斗的游戏
The deathmatch is superb.
多人死斗模式真是好玩得不得了
I'll remember where the railgun in The Edge is until I'm dead.
我在死之前永远想不起来电磁炮在哪里
Hard+ it is, because it can't possibly be as degrading as
最高难度就是这样，因为我经常被高手欺负
being constantly gibbed by someone named Slimshady99xx
经常被这个恶霸打死
Hard+ is like hard,
最高难度和困难难度大致相同
but the enemies don't flinch, they attack faster and have more health.
但是敌人不会退缩，攻击更快，而且血量更多
Most of the time I didn't even notice, except here:
大多数时候我都体会不到，除了这里......
Yeah, fuck that guy.
没错，我记住你了
Anyway I think it's time to start this less than strange journey into Id's dark age.
无论如何，我该开始这段不那么奇怪的旅程了，体会id的黑暗时光
That's not to say Quake II isn't a bad game, it isn't.
当然，这不意味着《雷神之锤II》是个差劲的游戏
It's exactly what I would expect from every Id game that came after it,
我觉得id在此之后发布的游戏都差不多这个风格
until Doom 2016, and then Doom Eternal
直到《毁灭战士2016》和《毁灭战士：永恒》
Listen, Doom Eternal is so slick and intricate and
没错，《毁灭战士：永恒》打磨得很复杂精细
I can't imagine the company being able to make a game as impressive again.
我都想不到这公司还能再次做出如此让人印象深刻的游戏了
Where Doom 2016 was an evolution of Id's formula,
《毁灭战士2016》算是id风格的进化
Doom Eternal was a redefinition of everything we thought could be done with it.
《毁灭战士：永恒》就是再次定义了这个流派的无限可能性了
Quake 2 is probably the least that can be done with it:
然而《雷神之锤II》在发掘可能性方面就差点意思了
a technical marvel that is a good action game;
科幻风很好，一个好的动作游戏，并且到处血肉横飞
a well-oiled machine fueled by blood and explosions.
And if Quake 2 is the worst game your studio would put out then, man, that's fine,
再说，《雷神之锤II》要是这个公司出的最差游戏的话，那也没啥
But RAGE is worse.
不过RAGE更差:-(
注：id公司于2011出品的游戏
Oh, boy when we get to RAGE...
天啊，要说到RAGE......
"Our radio tower up on the hill stopped working. We need someone to fix it."
“我们山上的广播塔停止工作了，我们得找人修一下”
"Eh, probably just out of alignment."
“应该只是哪个部件需要对齐一下”
"You get it fixed for me, and I'll give you a shotgun. Good luck.
“你给我修好了，我就给你把霰弹枪，祝你好运”
"This should be an easy job."
“这活应该不难”
"Well, not bad, stranger!"
“干得不错，陌生人！”
II. 游戏原声
Oh, can we talk about the soundtrack first?
哇，我能先说游戏原声吗？
Because it's BEAUTIFUL.
因为真是好听得不得了
It's not ambient Trent Reznor nightmare fuel,
他不是Trent Reznor制作的那种恐怖氛围音乐
It's hard, fast, wonderful metal. The stuff Bobby Prince wanted to do.
又重又硬，完美的重金属。正是Bobby Prince想做的那种
Except now they can put it on a CD and play it in-game!
不过这个可以刻进CD,在游戏里欣赏
It's soooo good!
真是好极～了
It was made by Sonic Mayhem, which is a person who's name is..
这些音乐由Sonic Mayhem编曲，他的真名嘛......
I'm not even going to try and pronounce that.
我都不知道我该怎么读:-P
It's one of those soundtracks you can pop into your CD player,
像这种音乐，我们可以直接插进CD播放机
(A thing we used to do)
(当时我们经常这么干)
And listen to it *without* the game!
然后可以在不玩游戏的时候欣赏
It absolutely shreds, adds so much to the action.
真的很干脆利落，给游戏增添了很多动力
BGM: Quad Machine by Sonic Mayhem
III. 血与铁
The basic story of Quake II is that you are Bitterman.
游戏的大致剧情是，你是Bitterman
Look at that, a named protagonist!
好家伙，主角居然有个名字
And your pod crashes onto Stroggos, planet of the Stroggs
你的吊仓在Stroggos族的星球上坠落
A sinister race of aliens that fuses human or alien tissue with metal,
Stroggos族十分邪恶，将人类或是外星人啥的焊接上钢铁
like The Borg but bloodier and more savage.
有点像赛博人，不过更加暴力，野蛮
..and with explosions.
而且还能爆炸:-P
And only one of these monsters has a shield
而且只有一类有护盾
Your main objective, out of all the other ones that gentle nag you throughout the game,
你主要的任务，除去那些整个游戏里都有的分支任务外
Is to destroy the Big Gun.
就是去摧毁大炮
Is to destroy the BIG Gun.
Brian Johnson *1
Is to destroy the BIG GUN.
就是去摧毁大炮
After you've made your way through military installations,
你进入了一个军事设施，然后城市，又一个军事设施，最后是宫殿
the city, other military installations, the palace,
Quake II doesn't have a lot of variety in it's settings.
《雷神之锤II》在关卡交互上没啥多样性
It does what it can with them,
基本上按下后就是那些事情
In terms of level design it has a kind of Hexen-like hub system
尽管关卡设计中实现了《毁灭巫师》那样的多地图系统
that lets you travel back-and-forth between areas
可以让你在前后关卡之间无缝穿梭
It's not used extensively for anything important, you go to this map,
不过这没有在什么重要步骤方面使用，你走进了这个地图
then complete an objective that opens up an area on the previous map,
然后完成了一项任务，开起之前地图的某个地方
go there, and by the time you're done
你走了进去，然后你完成任务后
you might not even know you completed the mission
你也许都不知道你完成了一项任务
because everything you need to do is fairly obvious.
因为你需要干的事情过于熟悉了
Maybe I've played it too much, but the objectives seem to complete themselves
也许我玩得很多了，但是当你和Strogg战斗的时候
while you're battle the Strogg
任务之间的关系就能串起来了
It's never confusing, which I guess is a testament to
我从未迷糊过，也许这就体现出关卡设计师们的经验丰富了
the level designers, seasoned pros by this point.
The first hub starts off as soon as you crash and escape your pod
游戏的第一个部分就是你坠机后，你爬出来吊仓
here you are, armed with only a shitty little blaster,
你看到了这个场景，手里只有爆能枪
shooting the common low-level hitscanners.
威力只够打死几个小怪
..for like a minute until you come over here and get the shotgun
大约一分钟后，你得到了霰弹枪
It's not a bad shotgun, I always liked the look of it, even if it felt a little weak.
这霰弹枪还算可以，我喜欢它的外观，尽管有点不得劲
the game teaches you that there's breakable glass now.
游戏还告诉你玻璃可以打碎呢:-|
You can crouch, there's going to be a robot voice telling you..
你可以蹲下，还有一个电子合成声音告诉你
"COMPUTER UPDATED"
“任务已更新”
..every time your mission status changes
当你的任务状态改变的时候
You know immediately that this isn't Quake 1
你立刻感觉到这可不是初代《雷神之锤》
And if you were lucky enough to have one of those fancy 3D accelerator cards at the time,
如果你足够幸运，在当年有3D加速卡的话
It wasn't gonna look like Quake 1 either!
这看起来也不像初代《雷神之锤》
even in software mode the new lighting and particle effects were pretty impressive.
尽管软件渲染下，光照效果和粒子效果挺让人印象深刻的
Quake 2 RTX is kinda trash, though
不过光追版就很垃圾了
it runs badly and ruins the atmosphere Trent Reznor said that this game doesn't have.
跑起来不流畅，而且就连T.Reznor提到的那点没有的气氛都没了
Default settings make everything really bright
默认设置下，所有东西看起来都太亮了
and when you turn that down you still have to deal with texture bugs
如果关闭这些效果的话，你还要解决贴图错误
and WHAT THE FUCK DID THEY DO TO MY RAILGUN? :<
而且他们改的电磁炮是什么玩意？
It's all very shiny and suffers from
每个东西都很亮
adding HD textures to a game that wasn't designed for them
因为加载了并非为其设计的高清材质包
..at least it doesn't cost anything
不过至少是免费的:-P
注：https://github.com/NVIDIA/Q2RTX
Another new thing is an Inventory system
还有一个新玩意，就是储物系统
The first inventory item you'll pick up is a silencer..
你第一次拾起来的东西是消声器
the game has *useful* powerups, too. Quad Damage, Invulnerability,
当然，有用的东西也有。四倍伤害，无敌
a Toxin Suit.. which is useful in about 3 places throughout the whole game.
还有防护衣，整个游戏也就三个地方有用
A power shield too.. and I think that's it.
还有一个超级护甲，就这样......吧
..yeah, I save the powerups for when I need them, mostly for cheesing bosses.
我攒着这些道具，等到需要的时候再用，多数情况是打Boss
It's too bad you don't get nearly the number of
不过可惜的是，你在二代游戏中拿到的四倍伤害比一代时要少
Quad Damage power-ups as you do in Quake 1
rampages are a lot less frequent,
而rampage就更少了
I had maybe one or two during the whole game, and it seems like a complete non-factor.
貌似整个游戏最多见到一两个，看上去也无关紧要
Like it was in Doom 2016, where you just pick up a few during the whole campaign.
就像《毁灭战士2016》那样，整场大战下来没捡起多少东西
Quake II does have an atmosphere,
《雷神之锤II》的确有那种气氛
a foreboding sci-fi body horror thing going on.
那种不详的科幻气氛
Space Nazis made of flesh and metal to keep the Guns of Navarone influences
血与铁所铸就的太空坏蛋，很明显受到了那部电影的影响
The enemies may not flinch,
敌人也不退缩，步步紧逼
but they still do this thing where they continue attacking as they die,
不过他们在死的时候仍然在尝试攻击
which you can avoid by gibbing them.
当然，为避免这种现象，你可以将其打爆
They all gib.
你没听错，他们都能打爆
THEY ALL GIB!
他 们 都 能 打 爆！
.. it's *actually* pretty cool
真心觉得很酷的
You're moving along through this base shooting Strogg
你穿过基地，射杀Strogg们
who wont give you much trouble 'till the Enforcers
他们不会给你多少麻烦，直到你见到了Enforcers
Chaingunners? :< Fun..
有机关枪呀，好吧:-P
Slightly less of a problem when get the Machine Gun in the next level
在下关拿到小型机关枪后，稍微好对付了一些
SuperBart: 应该是minigun，怀疑原作者口误
which has recoil for some reason.
不过这枪还带反冲的
...what game do you think you are Quake 2?
你游戏设计师没事搞这些干嘛
Cut that shit out.
把刚那段剪了
It's still satisfying, because the game gives it to you super early
虽然玩起来还是很愉快，因为游戏很早就给你这把枪了
and lets you mow down the lower enemies with it.
But that's not what we're here for, we need to go to the secret level..
但这把枪可不是全部，我们需要去秘密关卡
once you get through the sewer
只要我们经过下水道:-P
Have a swim, go down this elevator
游个泳，上个电梯
and your objective changes from "Go to a thing loosely related to saving humanity" to
你的任务就由“做一些大致能对拯救人类有意义的事情”变成
"Find a powerful weapon".
“找到一个有威力的武器”
..and oh boy do you ever!
啊这......那就找吧
Quake 2's Super Shotgun lives up to the family legacy
《雷神之锤II》的超级霰弹枪算是继承了家族之光
It's pump action now, it sounds just as devastating as the Doom 2 Super Shotgun
现在是泵动式的了，听起来和《毁灭战士二》的一样，具有毁灭性
This should clarify that all the weapons in this game are not a problem
而这也能体现出这个游戏的武器都很不错
SuperBart: 我们辅导员说我们大类的专业都很不错，可是我不想去人工智能啊
I mean, they don't have any muzzle flashes for some goddamn reason, but whatever I guess.
当然，不知为啥，枪口也没有闪光，不过没啥关系
You'll pick up throwable grenades, too
你也拿到了手榴弹
which I don't really use. I like to save them until I get the Grenade Launcher.
不过我不经常使用，我攒着它，等有榴弹发射器的时候再用
In Hard+ mode you'll meet the two most dangerous enemies in the game in the first hub.
在“困难”模式下，你会在游戏的第一部分见到两个最危险的怪物
Ugghh, this one always weirded me out
天哪，这玩意真是腻味死我了
it'll suck your health dry with..
他会吸干你的体力，使用了......
Euughh..
:-(
And the Gunner, who really only becomes a huge problem on Hard+
还有Gunner，也就在“困难+”难度下有点困难，因为他攻击得更快
because he attacks faster
and I don't know if he's going to spam me with machine gun fire or grenades.
我也不知道他会朝我开枪，还是扔手榴弹
Early game you might benefit from crouching under the grenades if you're close enough,
游戏开始，如果你离手榴弹很近的话，你可以蹲下来，以减少伤害
I really prefer getting the Rocket Launcher or Railgun to deal with him.
不过我更乐意在之后，用火箭发射器或电磁炮来消灭他们
Before that you have the Super Shotgun..
在这之前，只能用超级霰弹枪了
I'd like to point out that none of this is "bad design", it checks all the boxes.
我想说一点，这些设计没一个是“坏设计”，至少肯定是千锤百炼了
Your enemies all make distinct sounds
你的敌人都能发出挺不错的音效，也有动作来给玩家合适的反应
and movements that provide proper feedback to the player
You walk into a room, you hear something, you know what's coming
你走近了一个房间，你听到了某些东西，你意识到可能要出事
"Trespasser!"
“阻挡一切！”
注：这玩意官方名字为Berserker
Oh yeah, the Berserker's are like kittens they're mostly harmless
这家伙就是纸打的老虎，也就叫得响
Their attack windup takes so long that it's your own fault if you get hit
他攻击时摆臂时间过长，所以你要被打到的话，该练练反应能力了
You meet a few other monsters in the first hub, the fliers, the barracuda sharks,
你在第一部分也能看到其他的敌人，诸如这两个
easily dealt with with the Super Shotgun.
拿超级霰弹枪很快就能处理掉
I don't think any of the monsters besides the Gunner or the Parasite actually annoy me,
我觉得除了开始说的那两个，其他的敌人都没那么烦人
they're not too difficult to deal with.
他们处理起来都不难
The enemies have some really cool idle animations too.
敌人也有很多很酷的默认动画
..be really hard to see them in-game with all the shooting, though.
不过在游戏中很难看到，毕竟一直在开枪打怪
0.o
阿姨，您多大了
What's your name, scumbag?!
你小子叫吗?!
"Trespasser!"
"毁坏者!"
Did your parents have any children that lived!?
你有兄弟姐妹吗!?
Oh shit, wait.. that is a dead guy
等会......这是个僵尸:-P
You know what? Never mind.
算了吧，下次再得嘞你
You remember when I said I usually stop playing this game
还记得我说过，我在Ammo Depot这关由于太厌倦而弃坑了吗？
around Ammo Depot because I get bored?
Well second hub starts with Ammo Depot,
好吧，游戏的第二部分开始就是这关
and I'm trying to remember why
我也一直在想为啥我会厌倦
You get the Chaingun around here and that's fun
你开始就能拿到机关枪，挺好的
even if it chews through your ammo.
尽管这玩意太费子弹
Maybe *because* it chews through your ammo.
也许就是其贼耗子弹才有的爽快感吧
I don't remember an FPS game before this that let you spit so much lead at an enemy at once.
我想不起来有啥FPS游戏让你能在一个敌人上面倾泻那么多的子弹
It's kind of amazing even if it is impractical.
虽然老这么做很不现实，但是还是很爽快的
But sometimes, just everyone now and then you run into a room
但你经常走进一个屋子，在5秒内打出200个子弹，把敌人都打爆
and gib everything in it by firing 200 bullets in about 5 seconds.
It's pretty satisfying!
真的很让人满足
IV. 还行吧
It's always around here that the game starts to lose me
这个地方经常能让我弃游
but why?
不过为何呢？
is it that I've already dealt with it's most difficult challenges?
是因为我已经打通了最高难度了吗？
The game doesn't think so.
这游戏可不这么认为
For some reason the game thinks that these Tanks are a problem,
也不知为嘛，这游戏把这些Tank当成很难对付的东西
even though I can spam the chaingun at them and avoid any rockets or energy blasts
不过我可以一直用机关枪打他，并躲避所有火箭和能量波
The first boss'd be better served with the Tank name.
我觉得第一个Boss更适合被叫做Tank
I mean, look at it!
你看看这玩意！
Talking about single segments of Quake 2 isn't really that exciting
要讲这个游戏每个部分都是干啥的话，就有些无聊了
where in other games you'll have specific levels
在其他游戏中，你会遇到很多其他关卡，可以争取更高的分数
and areas where you can consider high points,
Quake 2 feels like it maintains a certain consistency all the way through
这个游戏感觉像是在一直坚持某种特定的复杂
It's never bad, but also very little stands out.
确实不差，但根本没有脱颖而出的特点啊
So let's talk about the rest of the guns because they're great.
所以接下来的节目中，我要介绍其他的枪了，因为他们太好用了
The Grenade Launcher, I think it it feels better than Quake or Quake 3's grenade launcher.
先是榴弹发射器，我觉得手感比一代和三代的好得太多了
The Rocket Launcher? Not quite as good as Quake 1's, but it's fine.
而火箭发射器比一代差劲一点，不过还好
The Hyperblaster has a wind-up for some goddamn reason..
高速爆能枪不知为啥，枪口还能旋转
but I find it's a good replacement for the Machine Gun anyway.
不过我觉得这玩意能代替机关枪
It's your standard rapid fire energy weapon.
就是很标准的快射速能量枪
The Railgun? Perfection.
电磁炮十分完美
Shadow Warrior may have had one first but Quake 2 had it best
也许Shadow Warrior先有的，不过《雷神之锤II》的最好
Quake 3 added a sound queue to help the player know when it was ready to fire again
《雷神之锤III》的加入了一系列声音，提醒玩家可以再次发炮
which is cool, otherwise it seems like railguns may have peaked with the Quake series.
挺好的，要不然我觉得雷神之锤系列的电磁炮也就这样了
And the BFG10K, you all know what it is and what it does.
还有BFG10K，一听就知道这是干啥的了
The first real attempt to upgrade the classic BFG
头一回升级传统的BFG9K
to make it not based on hacked-together Doom engine nonsense.
显得和之前毁灭战士的那玩意没啥关系
It's a big green ball that now also shoots lasers to nearby targets as it passes by
他射出一个大绿球，空中飞行的同时还对其附近的敌人发射激光
so now you've got what I call "The ID Arsenal",
而这就算是“id军械库”的所有内容了
the formula that ID games would more or less follow
基本上id的游戏或多或少都会遵循的惯例
until like Doom 2016, give or take a super shotgun or a railgun here and there.
直到《毁灭战士2016》，会给你一个霰弹枪或是电磁炮啥的
Pistol
手枪啊
Shotgun
霰弹枪啊
Super Shotgun
超级霰弹枪啊
Light automatic weapon
轻型自动化武器啊
Heavy automatic weapon
重型自动化武器啊
Rocket Launcher
火箭发射器啊
Rapid fire energy pew-pew gun
快射速能量枪啊
(Quake 3 has two of those)
（《雷神之锤III》有两种）
Railgun
电磁炮啊
BFG
还有BFG
..it's the way it goes, it's like a brand, an ID brand.
就这些了，简直像个标杆，可称之为id标杆
I guess that's what sticks with me most and
我觉得就是这点，让我耿耿于怀
why Quake 2 sometimes leaves a sour taste in my mouth
也是为啥这个游戏让我觉得心里很拧巴
ID became a brand.
id已然是个标杆了
And while there was a little wiggle room when it came to the formula
而对于这种游戏模式，他们倒是会有微调
Doom 3 is scary, Rage has 3 side quests..
《毁灭战士3》是恐怖风格，Rage有三条支线任务
it feels like there wasn't any room for anything game-changing anymore
就好像游戏除了技术革新，游戏性没啥变化了
DOOM3引擎(id Tech 4)：光影效果
Rage 引擎(id Tech 5)：大贴图快速加载
if it wasn't the technology.
And that technology lead to games taking longer and longer to make
而技术的开发可谓拖了游戏开发的后腿
Doom 3 took four years, Rage took seven!
《毁灭战士3》花了4年，而Rage花了7年!
ID Software is, and will probably forever be tech wizards.
id一直是，而且将永远是一个技术先行者
I wanted to go into this like other Pro videos
我本想和我做过的其他游戏介绍视频一样，介绍这个游戏
here are the enemies, here are the weapons, here's how these work together..
敌人长这样，武器是这些，他们是这样组合的
but you already know!
但你们早就知道了
There's a few secret levels to find, Sudden Death is actually pretty unique
游戏中有一些秘密关卡，Sudden Death实际上很独特
if you can jump up past this waterfall in Receiving Center
你在Receiving Center这关跳过这个瀑布
you'll be taken straight to Sudden Death,
你就会被带到Sudden Death
to collect as many powerups and weapons as you can
在很短的时间内收集尽量多的增强道具和武器
in the small amount of time it gives you.
The third secret level, much closer to the end,
快到游戏结尾时，有第三个秘密关卡
is a low-gravity space station full of flying enemies.
是一个低重力太空站，全都是飞行怪物
..it sure is that!
真就这味呗:-P
I didn't hate playing Quake 2 again,
再玩一次《雷神之锤II》也没什么
but if you were to ask me what parts I specifically remember
但你要是问我游戏哪里很精彩的话
I couldn't tell you much.
我没啥可说的啊
There was a mine full of Mutants.. three bosses they never caused me much trouble
Mine关有很多Mutants，有三个Boss，都不难处理
and it would be hard for me to really differentiate between them.
而且这三个Boss也没多大区别
Tank thing, flying thing, and the final boss had a BFG and two forms.
有一个坦克，有一个能飞，最终Boss有两种类型的BFG
I played through Quake 2, took me about 6 hours minus the time I spent taking notes
我把《雷神之锤II》通关了，花了我小6个小时记笔记
which going over them again couldn't have been very long..
而笔记很快就能看完......
"高速爆能枪跟机关枪差不多，不过更容易瞄准"
"好用的远距离武器在游戏开始没有"
"游戏原声很好听"
"没被触发的敌人更好杀"
"注意Strogg读音，否则有人钻牛角尖"
"Torture chambers那关真不好玩"
This level always gives me trouble
Torture chambers 经常让我陷入困境
hardest map in the game as far as I'm concerned
我所注意到的最困难的一关
even when you meet the Iron Maidens.
就算遇见了Iron Maidens，也不是事
They can be deal with quickly, a couple rockets or a couple railgun shots,
很快就能处理掉，俩火箭或两枪电磁炮就够了
But these menacing hallways even include a mini sewer section..
但是过道很危险，甚至有个小型下水道环节:-P
with a Parasite in it.
里面有一个Parasite
As-if they predicted that 23 years later some asshole would come along
就好像他们知道23年后，会有人来到这里
and use it for a dumb gag I can't escape.
将其作为一个差劲包袱录进视频，我还逃不出去
If I stop doing it the joke falls apart
如果我不这么做的话，就没啥笑话了
because it relies on me being petty enough to count every single one every time.
因为我每次得费老大劲数清每一个下水道环节
I guess things liven-up when you get towards the big gun
我觉得当我们接近大炮的时候，事情就明显了起来
Brian Johnson * 2
and that map with the air strike is cool!
而且还有空袭呢
I have to disable the supply train that the Strogg are using
我按照指示，摧毁了Strogg的补给火车
I don't know what's on that train, or why it's important, it doesnt matter.
我不知那里面有啥，任务有啥重要的，不过没关系
The mission objectives of Quake 2 are effective at
《雷神之锤II》的任务设计在描述
portraying a certain scope of the human operations on Stroggos.
人类对Stroggos的任务上面还挺让人明白的
You are a one man army, no-one else can get to the surface until we destroy the big gun.
你孤军深入，其他人无法登陆，直至你摧毁了大炮
Brain Johnson * 3
And to do that we have to complete all of these secondary objectives
为达成此目标，我们得完成一系列次要目标
I'm not entirely sure how this war started in the first place,
我对这场战争是如何开始的，表示不甚了解
SuperBart：所以有些小学生(非字面义)无故攻击这个，攻击那个，为啥呢:-(
there's a little bit in the intro that explains that we were attacked.
游戏开始的引入部分倒是介绍了为啥我们受到了攻击
The intro has what sounds like news reports explaining that the Strogg attacked major cities
开始的部分像新闻简报，说Strogg攻击了主要城市
and that our brave heroes were taking the fight to them.
而我们的单人英雄正在和其鏖战
SuperBart：瓦尔特保卫萨达热窝即视感？
Not a bad setup, make those alien bastards pay!
背景还行，那些外星混蛋会付出代价的
The kind of righteous bloodshed that's expressed
有点像《毁灭战士》和初代《雷神之锤》说明书中提到的正义大战
in a paragraph in the Doom and Quake manuals
as an excuse to kill everything that moves.
也就是你消灭游戏中一切生灵的借口
These cutscenes are a new feature of Quake 2
过场动画是《雷神之锤II》的新特性
..and I don't think they help it.
然而我觉得没啥用
A radio voice gives you objectives and
机器人声音告诉你任务
游戏两部分之间有电脑屏幕，和类似的机器人声音
between units a computer screen with a similarly robotic voice
shows you a map and tells you what you'll being doing later.
展示地图，并告诉你接下来要做什么
初
初始
初始化
初始化扫
初始化扫描
初始化扫描中
正在搜索
已找到
目
目标
目标已
目标已被
目标已被定
目标已被定位
正
正在
正在离
正在离开
正在离开基
正在离开基地
进
进入
进入掩
进入掩体
进入掩体区
进入掩体区域
摧
摧毁
摧毁敌
摧毁敌方
摧毁敌方后
摧毁敌方后勤
摧毁敌方后勤保
摧毁敌方后勤保障
摧毁敌方后勤保障列
摧毁敌方后勤保障列车
I'm sorry, the what?
等会，嘛玩意？
已找到
进入掩体区域
摧毁敌方后勤保障列车
摧毁敌方
摧毁敌方后
摧毁敌方后勤
摧毁敌方后勤保
摧毁敌方后勤保障
摧毁敌方后勤保障列
摧毁敌方后勤保障列车
The 'Str-ah-g'?
念Str-ah-g?
"As these brave soldiers took the fight to the 'Str-oag's home planet.."
当这些勇敢的战士在'Str-oag'的母星上战斗时
The 'Str-oag'?
又念Str-oag?
已找到
关
关闭
关闭敌
关闭敌方
关闭敌方炼
关闭敌方炼油
关闭敌方炼油厂
...I can't win, I give up.
算了，不想搞明白了
Calling this game "story-driven" is like calling Jurassic Park "science-driven."
如果这游戏算故事推动型的话，那《侏罗记公园》就是科普电影了
This is still the flea circus.
还是那老一套呗
John Carmack：游戏玩得爽就行了，管他什么剧情呢
Adding further context to it only raises more questions
故事再加料，恐怕就经不起推敲了
你好，CV-11
请摧毁反应堆
Yeah, I'm working on it!
是啊，我正干呢
请摧毁反应堆
不要去大炮那里
But that's what the whole fucking game is about! It's about the BIG GUN!
但整个游戏都是为了这玩意，不就是搞掉大炮吗
不要去大炮那里
返回冷却工厂
V.我游不动了
It just feels like another sewer..
总觉得又是一个下水道部分
another maze of pipes, ramps and metal..
又一个管道迷宫，坡道，金属啥的
注："Design is law"(设计是规则)是John Romero的名言
Dopefish是Commander Keen的梗，算是Tom Hall很上心的了
Oh..
emmm
Oh, god..
天哪
Oh god, please no...
不要这样啊
Don't do the Dopefish dirty like this!
不要把Dopefish搞这这样
Not like this! :(
别搞成这样啊！
VI. 敌人的核心
Towards the end as you're headed into the Palace you find the Tank Commanders,
到游戏结尾，你进入了宫殿，看到了Tank Commanders
Who are upgraded versions of the tanks from earlier
也就是之前Tank的升级版
Who are obviously big bastards who take a lot of your ammo to deal with.
显然又大又难缠，需要费很多子弹处理
The Tank Commanders are like the elite guards of the Strogg,
这玩意相当于Strogg中的精英保镖了
And then it's at the end of this palace level where this happens..
而在宫殿部分的末尾，还有这件事情
“追随我吧，人类。”
I'm having an interaction with another character
我是在和另一个角色对话吧
that isn't just a staticky voice on the other end of
他应该不止是广播另一头
the radio saying vague army man things at me?
向我说一些意义不明话语的人吧
You'd think getting here would be difficult..
你觉得到这里，游戏会变得很难
And it is! Occasionally..
有时还真是这样
Especially if you have one of those source ports
尤其是某些改进引擎里的准星
where the crosshair's are big, blocky, ugly things that hurt my eyes.
是那种又大，又碍眼的丑陋玩意
...fucking disgusting.
太辣眼睛了
Civvie实际上很喜欢Yamagi Quake 2，并认其为该改进引擎为该游戏为现代电脑的移植版
But this game isn't made to be a dick to you
但这游戏不会为难你
It doesn't have Spawns or Arch-viles
这游戏没有复活机制，没有《毁灭战士》里的火人
Nothing blinds you, or outmaneuvers you, or really challenges you that much..
没有碍眼的东西，没有拼技术的东西，没有啥有挑战性
Not even the Strogg leader!
甚至Strogg族的首领也没那么难打
I'm invulnerable for half of the fight, and for the other half I can just run circles around him.
和他战斗，前一半时间我无敌，后一半时间我就绕圈打他
I guess it's better than any of the boss fights in Quake 1, because it's a *boss* fight.
我觉得这个Boss战比初代《雷神之锤》的任意一场都要好
因为这真是一场Boss战
and most of the Doom ones now that I think about it.
兴许也比《毁灭战士》的任意一场都要好
This bit at the end with the animation, the torso trying to re-attach to the legs
最后的一点细节，Boss打败后尝试重新接上他的腿
Is cool and memorable!
让人印象很深刻
and I feel like the rest of the game rarely lives up to this.
我觉得这游戏的其他部分很少有能让人印象深刻的地方了
The player is guided through Quake 2 without much resistance.
玩家在整个游戏中，没有遇到多少阻挡
SuperBart：不像《半条命》，经常卡机关，难受死了。
the game just wants you to dive in and have fun, and dying isn't very fun!
游戏就想让你认真好好玩，而经常挂掉就没那么有趣了
One of the things I noticed when playing a little of the first Quake 2 expansion by Xatrix
我稍微玩《雷神之锤II》第一个扩展包的时候
was that it was significantly more difficult than the main campaign.
觉得比主线战役要困难得许多
This is true of most expansion packs, but the important part is *why*.
很多扩展包都这样，但主要是为什么
You're thrown into a sewer level pretty early..
你很快就会遇到下水道关卡:-P
And something that vanilla Quake II never really prepared you for
还有一件东西，原版《雷神之锤II》没有展示给你
was an abundance of rudely placed hitscanners.
就是大量骚走位的枪手
ID Software is made up of professionals
id由很多专业游戏设计师
Who make very deliberate design choices..
他们设计关卡的时候，很深思熟虑
Xatrix, who up to this point had worked on Redneck Rampage,
而这时刚完工Redneck Rampage的Xatrix
didn't care about the players feelings..
根本不考虑玩家的感受
SuperBart：Bob Fripp从来不考虑我们需要在网上欣赏King Crimson的需求
For fuck's sake! These introductory enemies, whatever they are,
天哪，一开始那个怪物，不管是个嘛
leap around like the Mutants and take a solid three to five shells to bring down!
和Mutants一样跳来跳去，需要三五发霰弹枪全中才能搞定
ID Software, at least in Quake 2, wanted to keep the power fantasy
id公司，至少开发《雷神之锤II》的时候，想保持一种激情和幻想
but like a lot of developers, lost the idea that
但和其他的开发者一样，忽略了
the fantasy only works if you overcome something.
这些幻想得建立在解决实际东西的基础上
not if you feel like you're operating the machine properly.
而不是一种貌似在正确操作机器的感觉
The other thing that sticks out in my mind of Quake II probably more than anything else
而另一个让我印象深刻的东西，也许比其他的更印象深刻的
Is the secret developer's room.
是秘密开发者画廊
It is a cool Easter Egg, and I really like it.
挺好的游戏彩蛋，我很喜欢
but there's more here..
不过还不止于此
What was happening at ID Software during this?
id在开发游戏的时候，经历了什么
Besides the public bitchyness towards Ion Storm and Romero, and Daikatana..
除了公开嘲讽Ion Storm, John Romero和Daikatana啥的
The story to this, of course, is hinted at in Masters of Doom
当然，这些故事都隐藏在这本书里
down to the easter egg room designed by Tim Willits himself.
说这个彩蛋是由Tim Willits亲自设计的
每一个画像都能触发出某种动画
在Tim看来，能反映出这些人的性格
而Carmack在人接近他的时候，躲进地板里了
Carmack had dissapeared, locking himself away in coding
这家伙自己消失了，一头埋进开发的苦海
and within a year artist Adrian Carmack, no relation, would want out of ID Software
在一年内，和前面没亲戚关系的Adrian Carmack想退出公司了
felling that the company was just making the same game over and over again
觉得这个公司一直在不停地做同一种游戏
American McGee and Adrian Carmack would be gone soon enough,
American McGee 和 Adrian Carmack 不久后就走了
McGee getting the same treatment Romero and Tom Hall got for the most part
McGee在很多方面遭遇了和Romero和Hall相同的待遇
And when you hit Carmack's button..
而当你按了他的按钮后
No, no...
天哪
John, John what are you doing?
您......您这是在干嘛？
No! Let me out!
不，让我出去！
Make it stop!
停下这一切！
Make it stop.. make it stop..
停下这一切，停下这一切......
Yeah, I know there's a self-destruct happening and the station is about to explode
我知道自毁程序已经启动，空间站即将爆炸
but that doesn't matter, it's the end of the game and Bitterman survives.
不过跟主角没关系，游戏结束了，Bitterman活了下来
Quake 2 runs and plays like one of Carmack's Ferrari's,
《雷神之锤II》玩起来就像那个人的一辆法拉利跑车
impressive, pretty, and powerful.
印象深刻，外表亮丽，激情畅快
But there's only so much a car can offer you if you've got a tiny penis.
不过你玩得少的话，也就这些了
SuperBart：我故意曲解了意思，有更好的理解可以弹幕覆盖(只要不是原意)
本视频由SuperBart翻译
原作者Civvie 11发布于2020年8月21日
原来的片尾曲是游戏《龙霸三合会》的How'd I Do
我给改成了AC/DC的Big Gun
赞助原作者：https://www.patreon.com/civvie11
字幕下载：https://github.com/BenderBolg/Subtitles